Guide to the Harry W. Selden Right Wing Materials Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Harry W. Selden right wing materials collection
1952-2016
MS 2069
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.83
(3 boxes)
The collection comprises pamphlets, newsletters, and other materials collected by Harry W. Selden and concerning conservative and right-wing politics and activism from the 1950s to the 1980s. Materials include newsletters, pamphlets, mass mailings, flyers, press clippings and photocopies, correspondence, and other printed and published materials. The material covers a wide range of topics, including the United Nations, disarmament, anti-communism, and Republican and conservative politics, and represents a large number of right-wing organizations. The collection also includes pamphlets and flyers for political candidates, primarily Republicans, along with a small number of newsletters and pamphlets from left-wing organizations. Some materials have handwritten notes and underlining by an unidentified author, possibly Selden. The collection also includes a partial inventory, possibly prepared in the 2010s.
Selden, Harry Wythe, 1915-2003
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises pamphlets, newsletters, and other materials collected by Harry W. Selden and concerning conservative and right-wing politics and activism from the 1950s to the 1980s. Materials include newsletters, pamphlets, mass mailings, flyers, press clippings and photocopies, correspondence, and other printed and published materials. The material covers a wide range of topics, including the United Nations, disarmament, anti-communism, and Republican and conservative politics, and represents a large number of right-wing organizations. The collection also includes pamphlets and flyers for political candidates, primarily Republicans, along with a small number of newsletters and pamphlets from left-wing organizations. Some materials have handwritten notes and underlining by an unidentified author, possibly Selden. The collection also includes a partial inventory, possibly prepared in the 2010s.
Biographical / Historical
Harry Wythe Selden (1915-2003) was a Virginia farmer and John Birch Society member. Selden was born in Virginia on December 21, 1915 and worked on his family's dairy farm in Mathews County, Virginia (near Hampton) until 1947, when he moved to the Mechanicsville, Virginia area to farm. He returned to Hampton in 1991. Selden was a lifetime member of the John Birch Society and served as its state coordinator and official spokesman. He was a frequent writer of letters to newspaper editorial pages and an active teacher and officer in local churches. Selden married twice and had two daughters and four step-children. He died in 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in five series: I. Pamphlets, newsletters, and other materials, circa 1950s-circa 1980s. II. Subject files, circa 1950s-circa 1980s. III. Correspondence, 1968-1969. IV. News clippings and reprints, 1959-1975. V. Ephemera, circa 1960s-circa 2010s.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Kaplanoff Librarian for American History, 2016
Conservatism -- United States; Right and Left (Political Science); Anti-communist movements -- United States; United States -- Politics and government; United States -- Foreign relations; Selden, Harry Wythe, 1915-2003; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United Nations
- Pamphlets, newsletters, and other materials, 1952-1984; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of pamphlets, newsletters, mass mailings, flyers, and other printed matter related to right-wing politics and activism. Materials cover a wide range of topics and represent a large number of organizations and publications. Also included are pamphlets and campaign materials for and against various political candidates, mostly Republicans. Materials also include reprints of speeches and bills from the Congressional Record, along with a small number of publications from left-wing organizations and political candidates.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged as received from the donor.
  - Materials, 1952-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Materials, 1961-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Subject files, 1958-1977; Series II
  This series consists of pamphlets, newsletters, mass mailings, and other printed and published materials, sorted into subject files. Note that many of the materials in these files also contain information on other subjects, and substantial additional material on many of these subjects can be found in the other series in this collection.
  Series II is arranged as received from the donor.
  - Disarmament, 1962-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Disarmament, 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Education, 1961-1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Education, circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Foreign aid, 1958-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Foreign aid, circa 1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Institute for American Democracy (I.A.D.), 1967-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Liberty Amendment, circa 1963-circa 1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Liberty Lobby, 1964-1974, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Roberts, Archibald E., 1962-1971, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Roberts, Archibald E., circa 1961-circa 1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sensitivity training, 1968-1969, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Wallace, George C., 1967, undated (Box 2, Folder 9-10)
  - Wallace, George C., 1967-1970, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Women's movement, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women's movement, 1973-1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1968-1969; Series III
  This series consists of a small amount of correspondence, primarily drafts or copies of letters to the editorial page of local newspapers, sent by Selden or others. In some cases, a newspaper clipping of the published letter is attached. Some similar correspondence can be found in the Sensitivity Training subject file in Series II.
  Series III is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- News clippings and reprints, 1959-1975; Series IV
  This series consists of a small number of newspaper and magazine clippings and reprints. Materials relate to a variety of topics, including national security, law enforcement, and right-wing politics and organizations.
  Series IV is arranged as received from the donor.
  - Clippings and reprints, 1959-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Ephemera, circa 1960s-circa 2010s; Series V
  This series consists of a cardboard sign and a partial collection inventory. The cardboard sign (or poster) advertises a Carl McIntire speaking event in Colonial Heights, Virginia. The sign is incomplete; it has been cut into a smaller size, apparently for use as a file divider. The partial collection inventory appears to have been created in the 2010s, possibly by a manuscript dealer.
  Series V is arranged as received from the donor.
  - Ephemera, circa 1960s-circa 2010s (Box 3, Folder 8)